Guide to the Gay Men's Health Crisis records
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Gay Men's Health Crisis records
1975-1978, 1982-1999
1982-1993
MssCol 1126
1126
Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
167.26 linear feet 407 Boxes, 3 oversized folders, 1 tube
The Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC), America's oldest AIDS organization, formed in 1982, serves to educate the public about HIV/AIDS, provide care services for People with AIDS (PWAs), and advocate at all levels of government for fair AIDS policies. It is a volunteer-supported, community-based organization that provides programs to clients and members of the general public regardless of HIV status, gender, or sexual orientation. The records document the three aspects of GMHC's activities and contain correspondence, memoranda, minutes, pamphlets, photographs, posters, questionnaires, reports, surveys, video recordings, and other material. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, and reports regarding GMHC's safe sex education programs and client services.
Introduction
The Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC), America's oldest AIDS organization, organized in 1982, serves to educate the public about HIV/AIDS, provide care services for People with AIDS (PWAs), and advocate at all levels of government for fair AIDS policies. It is a volunteer-supported, community-based organization that provides programs to clients and members of the general public regardless of HIV status, gender, or sexual orientation.
GMHC was founded by six gay men, Nathan Fain, Larry Kramer, Lawrence Mass, Paul Popham, Paul Rapoport, and Edmund White, at Kramer's Manhattan apartment on January 4, 1982. They had all been part of an earlier gathering at Kramer's on August 11, 1981, where Dr. Alvin Friedman-Kien discussed the "gay cancer" that was affecting their friends and lovers. Over $6,600 was raised at that meeting for research into Kaposi's sarcoma at New York University's Medical Center. When the six met in January 1982, they discussed raising more funds for research and organized GMHC's first major event at the Paradise Garage on April 8. The event was called Showers and $50,000 was raised.
While Showers was a success, the group realized that they could do more than simply raise money to help those affected. They decided to try to answer the many questions people had about the disease. The first service provided by the organization was the Hotline, which began in May as an answering machine in the apartment of volunteer, Rodger McFarlane, who later became the organization's second executive director. On the first night, 100 calls were received. While many of the questions could be answered over the phone, some of them required the help of medical, legal, and other professionals to answer. As there was no social service agency to which GMHC could direct these callers, they created the Patient Services Division to provide further help.
Service
In September, Dr. Ken Wein joined as the first Clinical Director and organized the Crisis Intervention Counselors. The Counselors assisted men who had recently fallen ill and who called the Hotline, were otherwise referred to GMHC, needed assistance maneuvering through the health care system, required help at home, or sought other support that could not be provided over the phone. At this time, McFarlane and others had been spending their spare time caring for friends and lovers who were neither able to take care of themselves at home nor represent their own best interests within the health care system. The situation in hospitals was especially critical as these men had to take on the duties of hospital workers, who refused to touch patients or enter their rooms to deliver food.
GMHC created the Buddy Program that September to consolidate the work of these men and to develop a program to train volunteers in assisting PWAs. The program began with 20 men who were on call 24 hours a day to provide assistance, but quickly grew as more men were affected by the disease. The program was staffed entirely of volunteers and initially consisted of people helping friends and lovers affected by AIDS with basic tasks such as grocery shopping, laundry, pet care, as well as spending time with the PWAs. As alarm spread about the disease and hospital staff refused to care for PWAs, Buddies also began to provide nursing care for PWAs and act as intermediaries with social and medical services. A new volunteer position was created to handle the latter and was called Crisis Intervention Worker (CIW). A handful of registered nurses volunteered at GMHC to train people in basic care (bathing, changing, feeding, etc.) of patients.
In 1985, the volunteer position of Crisis Management Partner (CMP) was created and combined the duties of a Buddy and a CIW. CMPs were assigned to PWAs with a number of emotional and physical needs.
As the AIDS epidemic grew and more people became infected, Client Services expanded to provide additional services for PWAs who were able to leave their homes through Recreation Services and Group Support Services programs. Recreation Services consisted of workshops in art, photography, writing, and bridge, trips to museums and other cultural institutions, movies, lunches, and parties. Group Support Services provided group counseling for PWAs and their care partners. These services provided a safe and informal setting to cope with the emotional and social problems associated with AIDS and fostered support networks. By 1985, there were ten groups specifically for PWAs, eleven for their care partners, as well as weekly walk-in groups for PWAs, care partners, family; groups for children with AIDS and their families; and groups for couples dealing with the disease.
Financial Advocacy Services, Legal Services, and the Office of the Ombudsman quickly followed. These services provided free advice to PWAs, kept them abreast of changes in federal services available to them, and provided advocacy for clients with problems with the healthcare system.
As PWAs began living longer and new treatments became available, Client Services began providing Nutrition Counseling, expanded its Recreation Services to include hot meals five days a week as well as other events, and created new Support Groups to meet the needs of communities within the larger AIDS community including women; Latinos and other people of color; and people with chemical dependencies.
By 1987, GMHC had created a position for a Deputy Executive Director for Program Operations which, following a restructuring of the organization in 1989, assumed responsibility for the administration of all of the Client Services programs: Client Advocacy, Education Department, Nutrition and Recreation Services, Legal Services, the Ombudsman Department, and the Volunteer Office.
In 1990, the enactment of the Ryan White CARE Act allowed GMHC to expand existing programs and create new ones. Within the next few years, GMHC created a number of programs which included a permanent Deaf AIDS Project (DAP), the Lesbian AIDS Project, and the Tuberculosis Education and Treatment Support Program. By 1993, Education once again became its own department, with its head reporting directly to the Executive Director.
Education
With the discovery of HIV in 1983, GMHC began its mission of education in earnest. Safe sex brochures and guidelines were published and distributed to bathhouses and gay bars. GMHC began staffing information tables around New York City with literature about AIDS and volunteers who could answer questions about AIDS and GMHC's services. Publication of the Health Letter began, providing statistics and research updates. GMHC was recognized as a leader in providing accurate and up-to-date information on AIDS and was consulted by the media, doctors, and health organizations.
In 1984 the Centers for Disease Control asked GMHC to assist them in creating public conferences on AIDS and in April 1985 they were part of the organizing committee of the first International AIDS Conference in Atlanta.
GMHC's AIDS Prevention program was developed in March 1985 once condoms were proven to be an effective means of preventing HIV transmission. It created programs to disseminate safe sex methods to the gay community and the growing number of other groups affected by the disease.
By October 1986, GMHC's client base had expanded to include heterosexual men and women, hemophiliacs, intravenous drug-users, and children. This led to innovations in AIDS education by GMHC, including the Medical Information Department which published Treatment Issues and provided information on new therapies; showed that safe sex could be fun through sexually explicit material, such as the Safer Sex Comix; and created outreach programs designed to adapt the original sex education classes to African-Americans, Latinos, and lesbians.
The Education Department began an audiovisual program in the mid-1980s which developed the weekly show Living with AIDS; produced public service announcements and safe sex videos which were shown at safe sex forums, sex clubs, and porn theatres; and created an oral history project in which some founders of GMHC were interviewed as well as a number of staff members in the late 1980s.
In the 1990s the department produced safe sex guidelines for lesbians; created programs for HIV-negative gay and bisexual men; expanded programs aimed at African-American and Latino men; and improved education for teens.
Advocacy
GMHC's advocacy work began in October 1983 with the funding of litigation brought by the Lambda Legal Defense Fund in the first AIDS discrimination case. A New York physician, Dr. Joseph Sonnabend, was threatened with eviction from his office because he was treating PWAs and the building's board felt that this would decrease property values. The case was decided in Sonnabend's favor.
Timothy J. Sweeney joined the staff of GMHC in 1986 as the Deputy Executive Director of Policy and created the Public Policy Department. The Department began to fight for increased funding for AIDS research, health care for PWAs, prevention programs, and greater civil rights protections for everyone affected by AIDS. The Department became an advocate at all levels of government for fair AIDS policies and was a leading member of the AIDS Action Council, the New York City HIV Health and Human Services Planning Council, and other groups of AIDS organizations.
Conclusion
At the time of this writing (2009), GMHC still provides many of the services for which it was created; but as AIDS has changed, so have its programs. The organization was created at a time when no one knew what AIDS was or how it was spread and it responded to the needs of its clients as they arose. In the beginning, GMHC provided hands-on, intensive care for PWAs in hospitals and their homes, disseminated timely and available information about AIDS to the affected populations, and provided legal advice. GMHC still provides these services, but now focuses on helping PWAs and HIV positive people to live healthy and productive lives; advocating government for fair policies and scientifically sound public health programs; and solving the legal, financial, and many other issues facing its clients.
GMHC maintains a timeline of important events in its history and the AIDS movement on its website www.gmhc.org.
The records of the Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC) document the three aspects of the organization's activities and contain brochures, correspondence, memoranda, minutes, pamphlets, photographs, posters, questionnaires, reports, sound recordings, surveys, video recordings, and other material. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, and reports regarding GMHC's safe sex education programs and client services. The collection is arranged by the departments of the organization, beginning with the Executive Director and continuing alphabetically from the Board of Directors through Women's Education Services. The largest series is the Education Department which contains material on GMHC's groundbreaking safe sex and AIDS prevention programs, dissemination of AIDS information, and training programs for health care workers. The Client Services records contain minutes of Buddy Teams, Crisis Intervention Workers, and Crisis Management Partners meetings. These minutes contain detailed information on how the volunteers assisted PWAs, the rapid spread of AIDS in the early days of the epidemic, and the physical and emotional toll these had on the PWAs and the volunteers. More information about each department can be found in the series notes.
The records reflect the explosive growth of GMHC and often contain overlapping or similar material within and across departments. During the first ten years of its existence, the organization adapted to the needs of its clients by expanding and creating departments and creating new programs and positions. The records reflect this growth and the subsequent reorganizations of GMHC. As a result of this, some series may contain material similar to another series or one unit may contain material relating to another unit. Such incidents are described at the series and subseries levels.
The Gay Men's Health Crisis Records are organized in the following series:
Series I. Board of Directors, 1982-1993
Series II. Executive Director, 1982-1996
Series III. Client Programs, 1988-1998
Series IV. Client Services, 1982-1999, n.d.
Series V. Communications Department, 1985-1997
Series VI. Development Department, 1982-1998, n.d.
Series VII. Education Department, 1982-1998, n.d.
Series VIII. Evaluation Research Department, 1989-1999, n.d.
Series IX. Legal Services Department, 1988, 1991-1995, n.d.
Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, 1975-1978, 1982-1997
Series XI. Photographs, 1987-1988, 1990s
Series XII. Public Policy Department, 1983-1997, n.d.
Series XIII. Staff Groups and Events, 1987-1995, n.d.
Series XIV. Substance Use Counseling and Education Program, 1993-1997, n.d.
Series XV. Women's Education Services, 1991, 1994-1997, n.d.
Series XVI. AudioVisual Department, 1985-1999, n.d.
Donated by the Gay Men's Health Crisis, July 1993, April and October 1994, October and December 1999, February 2000
ACT UP New York records. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
AIDS Activist Videotape collection. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
AIDS and Adolescents Network of New York records. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
Lawrence Mass papers. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
People with AIDS Coalition records. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
Advance notice required.
Audiovisual items that do not have an id number are not yet available. Readers should advise Division staff of their interest in any audiovisual material that is not yet available through the Reader Application Form: http://www.nypl.org/locations/tid/36/node/58098 The following files are closed until 2066 per the Gay Men's Health Crisis: Series II. Executive Director, Subseries A. Richard Dunne, Client complaints Series II. Executive Director, Subseries C. Timothy J. Sweeney, Client complaints Series II. Executive Director, Subseries D. Jeff Richardson, Client complaints Series IV. Client Services, Subseries C. Nutrition Assessment Forms Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries A. Administrative Files, AIDS discrimination documentation Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries A. Administrative Files, Case histories Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries A. Administrative Files, Correspondence Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries B. Case files Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries C. Resource Information files, Medical examiner Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries C. Resource Information files, Medical proxy Series X. Office of the Ombudsman, Subseries C. Resource Information files, Military Series XII. Public Policy, Subseries B. Alcohol and Other Drugs workgroup, Harm reduction Series XIV. Substance Use Counseling and Education Program, Subseries A. Administrative Files, Exit Interviews Series XIV. Substance Use Counseling and Education Program, Subseries A. Administrative Files, Participant histories Series XIV. Substance Use Counseling and Education Program, Subseries B. Groups, Group participant questionnaire.
Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc; AIDS (Disease); AIDS activists -- United States -- 20th century; Gay activists -- 20th century; Gay men -- Health and hygiene; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- Education; Brochures; Minutes; Pamphlets; Photographs; Posters; Questionnaires; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Series I. Board of Directors, 1982-1993; 18 boxes
  The Board of Directors at GMHC oversees all actions of the organization. The members of the first board were Paul Popham (also the first President of GMHC), Harry Diaz, Nathan Fain, Brad Frandsen, Joe Hernandez, Larry Kramer, Lawrence Mass, Larry McDevitt, and Joe Paschek. The first board meetings were held at members' apartments and covered all aspects of the organization, from the first fundraising events, the newsletter, and information and booths at Gay Pride Day. At the time, the board members were also employees and volunteers of GMHC and usually the only staff members of what eventually became the departments of the organization.
  This series contains minutes of board meetings, packets created to prepare executive directors for board meetings, correspondence with board members, and material from committees of the board.
  - I. A. Board Meeting Minutes, 1982-1992; 2.25 boxes
    The minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors begin in April 1982 with the first meetings of GMHC and continue through 1992. The minutes for the first few years reflect the organization's exponential growth from a handful of men meeting in an apartment to thousands of employees and volunteers working in a 12-story building. They contain information on the development of all aspects of GMHC, including its client services, educational mission, fundraising initiatives, and increasing public awareness about HIV/AIDS.
    - 1982-1988 May (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - 1988 Jun-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - I. B. Committees of the Board, 1982-1993; 2 boxes
    The Board of Directors created a number of committees to conduct business in specific areas. The bulk of material in this subseries comes from the Executive Committee and the Nominating Committee. The Executive Committee oversaw GMHC's budget, nominated members of the other committees, and reviewed the work of committees and departments at GMHC. The Nominating Committee oversaw elections to the Board of Directors.
    - Advisory Board, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Budget/Administration, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - By-laws revision, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Client services, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Directorship, 1985, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Education, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Executive
      - 1992-1993 Mar (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
      - 1993 Apr-Jun (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Finance, 1987-1988, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Government Affairs, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Nominating
      - 1984-1986, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4-8)
      - 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Personnel, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Victim Services, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Volunteer, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - I. C. Correspondence, 1982-1992, n.d.; 0.25 box (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
    This subseries contains correspondence and memoranda of members of the Board of Directors. Topics include acknowledgment of donations, requests for meetings with members of the medical and scientific communities, offers to volunteer time, knowledge, expertise, and other services, and internal policies. Further correspondence may be found in Series II. Executive Director and in the records of the specific departments.
  - I. D. Executive Directors, 1984-1993; 12.25 boxes
    This subseries contains reports compiled by the departments of GMHC and sent to the Executive Director in preparation for meetings with the Board of Directors. The files also contain agenda for the meetings, clippings, brochures and newsletters from other AIDS organizations, and budget information. Further material for each Executive Director can be found in Series II. Executive Director.
    - Rodger McFarlane, 1984-1985
      - 1984 Jan-May (Box 5, Folder 8-12)
      - 1984 Jun-1985 Nov 10 (Box 6, Folder 1-19)
    - Richard Dunne, 1985-1989
      - 1985-1986 May (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
      - 1986 Jun-1987 Feb (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
      - 1987 Mar-Sep (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
      - 1987 Oct-1988 Feb (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
      - 1988 Mar-Aug (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
      - 1988 Sep-1989 Mar (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
      - 1989 Apr-Jul (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
    - Jeffrey Braff, 1989-1990
      - 1989 Oct-Nov (Box 13, Folder 5-7)
      - 1989 Dec-1990 Jun (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
      - 1990 Jul (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Timothy J. Sweeney, 1990-1993
      - 1990 Aug-1991 Jan (Box 15, Folder 2-7)
      - 1991 Feb-Nov (Box 16, Folder 1-9)
      - 1991 Dec-1992 Aug (Box 17, Folder 1-7)
      - 1992 Sep-1993 (Box 18, Folder 1-9)
  - I. E. Miscellaneous, 1982-1992, n.d.; 1.25 boxes
    This subseries contains biographies of some members of the board, material from board retreats, and self-audits completed by board members.
    - Administrative highlights, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Biographies, 1985, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Board development, 1984-1992 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Chelsea Independent Democrats award, 1990 (Box 402)
    - Executive Director search, 1989, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - GMHC Newsletter, 1982-1983 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Greg Nigosian, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Mission statement, 1988, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Notes and organizational charts, 1982-1985, 1989, 1992, n.d (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Retreat, 1986, 1989-1991 (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
    - Self-audit, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Self-study criteria, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Standards of conduct, 1992, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Strategic plan, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Series II. Executive Director, 1982-1996; 57.5 boxes
  The Executive Director oversees the work of the various departments of GMHC and reports on these to the Board of Directors. Mel Rosen was the first Executive Director of GMHC, elected in August 1982 and serving until July of 1983 when he became the Director of the AIDS Institute. Rodger McFarlane returned to GMHC that month and served as Executive Director until June 1985. Richard Dunne (1985-1989), Jeffrey Braff (1989-1990), Timothy J. Sweeney (1990-1993), and Jeff Richardson (1993-1994) served in this position and are represented in this series.
  In the beginning of GMHC's history, the Executive Director was directly involved in all operations of the organization. McFarlane was responsible for moving the organization from its first office (a series of rooms in a building owned by Mel Cheren on West 22nd Street) to a larger office on West 18th Street and for formalizing some of GMHC's social programs, the Crisis Intervention Services and the Buddy Program. Dunne was the last Executive Director to have the same level of involvement with the development of the organization before it grew too large for any one person to have such a relationship.
  This series contains correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, and other material created by and sent to the Executive Director.
  - II. A. Richard Dunne, 1982-1991; 38 boxes